{"tossups": [{"question": "Two weeks after a Robert Geiger news story coined a name for this event, Hugh Bennett was made director of a new agency within the Interior Department. This event prompted the Soil Conservation Act, as it was partly caused by cattle overgrazing. Dorothea Lange\u2019s iconic photograph<em> Migrant Mother</em> depicts a family fleeing, for ten points, what event in which \u201cOkies\u201d attempted to move to California to avoid severe drought during the Great Depression?", "answer": "<b> Dust Bowl</b> (prompt on Great Depression)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Genseric captured this city after his betrothal to Eudocia was broken, and Alaric was able to capture this city after the death of Stilicho. The Battle of the Allia led to the capture of this city, which was forced to measure out ransom money using weighted scales by Brennus. Romulus Augustulus was deposed after the capture of this city in 476 AD. For ten points, name this city that was sacked several times during the fall of its Italy-based empire.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This kingdom was briefly controlled by Britain after the arrival of the HMS<em> Carysfort</em> in the Paulet Affair. Because Kalakaua had been intimidated into giving his power away, this kingdom\u2019s legal code was known as the Bayonet Constitution. Sanford Dole was appointed president of this kingdom shortly before it was annexed by William McKinley in 1898. For ten points, name this kingdom, that was ruled by Queen Liliuokalani and became the 50th US state.", "answer": "Kingdom of<b> Hawai\u2019i</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In what became known as this city\u2019s \u201cmile,\u201d a group of troops including Randall Ramaglia walked through RPG fire to a rally point at National Street. William Garrison commanded troops in a battle in this city that was part of the larger Operation Gothic Serpent; in that battle, troops under Mohammad Farah Aidid shot down two Black Hawk helicopters. For ten points, name this site of a 1993 battle involving Delta Force, the capital of Somalia.", "answer": "<b> Mogadishu</b> (accept<b> Hamar</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s promotion of pro-feminist policies was noted with the statement \u201cWomen hold up half the sky.\u201d This man began the Anti-Rightist Campaign after severe criticism led him to undo the Hundred Flowers Movement. In a failed attempt to modernize, this man encouraged peasants to create backyard furnaces during the Great Leap Forward, which began in 1958. For ten points, name this Communist chairman of China.", "answer": "<b> Mao</b> Zedong", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This President\u2019s doctrine pledged support to Middle Eastern governments, including military support for Camille Chamoun of Lebanon. Earl Warren was appointed as Chief Justice by this president a year before<em> Brown v. Board of Education</em> overturned the doctrine of \u201cseparate but equal.\u201d This president sent members of 101st Airborne Division to escort the Little Rock Nine. For ten points, name this president and former World War II Supreme Allied Commander.", "answer": "Dwight D(avid) \u201cIke\u201d<b> Eisenhower</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Members of this religious movement follow a ruleset called the Ordnung. One of the most conservative sects of this religious group, based in Nebraska, is known for its brown clothing. Some young people from this religious group are allowed to disobey norms in an exploratory period called Rumspringa. Lancaster County, Pennsylvania was a migration site for many members of, for ten points, what religious group known for living without the conveniences of modern technology?", "answer": "the<b> Amish</b> (prompt on Mennonites; prompt on Anabaptists)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "In this work, a character recounts the tale of a man named Er who revives on his funeral pyre and shares an account of the afterlife. A character in this work tries to explain the psyche by asking Glaucon to imagine a divided line and imagines a ring that makes the wearer invisible, the Ring of Gyges. The Allegory of the Cave and the benefits of rule under a \u201cphilosopher-king\u201d are described in, for ten points, what Platonic dialogue about justice and forms of government like oligarchy and democracy?", "answer": "The<b> Republic</b> (or<b> Politeia</b>)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "This battle was fought concurrently with an engagement at Wavre [wahv], leading to the absence of Emmanuel Grouchy. This battle is commemorated by the Lion\u2019s Mound, where a commander was shot off his horse. The arrival of Gebhard von Blucher\u2019s Prussians helped turn the tide of this battle, which ended the Hundred Days and forced its loser into exile in St. Helena. For ten points, name this 1815 battle in which Wellington defeated Napoleon for the last time.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Waterloo</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This dynasty was challenged by followers of the Celestial Masters, who launched the Five Pecks of Rice rebellion. Sima Qian [CHEE-an] compiled the<em> Records of the Grand Historian</em> under this dynasty, which became the first to use the civil service examination and linked itself to Rome using an overland trade route. For ten points, name this ancient dynasty that shares a name with the majority ethnic group of China.", "answer": "<b> Han</b> Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Greer County eventually was ruled to be part of this state after a dispute over the Adams-Onis Treaty with its southern neighbor. This state was assigned the Cimarron Territory in 1890 but was considered No Man\u2019s Land beforehand. The Unassigned Areas in this state were allocated by an 1889 land rush in which the \u201cSooners\u201d rushed across the border. For ten points, name this US state who has had several territorial disputes with its southern neighbor, Texas.", "answer": "<b> Oklahoma</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During a revolt named for this city, Eduard Goldstucker and the Writers Union went on television in an attempt to test free press laws. That revolt began when Jan Palach set himself on fire in this city\u2019s Wenceslas Square. Alexander Dubcek [doob-check] implemented \u201csocialism with a human face\u201d as part of a period of liberalization in 1968 known as this city\u2019s \u201cSpring.\u201d Soviet tanks eventually rolled into, for ten points, what capital city of Czechoslovakia?", "answer": "<b> Prague</b> (accept<b> Prague</b> Spring)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The masses of these entities are governed by the whole number rule as described by Francis Aston, whose cousin Margaret Todd suggested a name for these entities from the Greek for \u201cat the same place.\u201dOne of the 15 of these entities for carbon is used in radioactive dating, has a half-life of 5,700 years, and has eight neutrons instead of the more stable six-neutron form. For ten points, give this term for variants of the same element that have different atomic masses.", "answer": "<b> isotope</b>s", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In 1975, the CIA made estimates on this country\u2019s military efforts by counting the number of baseball diamonds built in Angola. Similarly, in 1970, the presence of a soccer field instead of baseball diamonds on Cazo Alcatraz in this country\u2019s port of Cienfuegos suggested to the CIA that the Soviet Union, not this country, was building naval infrastructure here. For ten points, name this country that hosted a set of Soviet-deployed missiles in 1962, leading to a namesake \u201ccrisis.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Cuba</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A ray of sunlight hit the casket of Winston Churchill as this song was being performed at his funeral. This song describes a figure who is seen \u201cin the watchfires of a hundred circling camps.\u201d This song, which was first published in the (+)</b><em><b> Atlantic Monthly</b></em><b> in 1862, inspired the title of Steinbeck\u2019s</b><em><b> The Grapes of Wrath</b></em><b>. The music of (*)</b> \u201cJohn Brown\u2019s Body\u201dwas used for, for ten points, what patriotic song by Julia Ward Howe that begins with the line \u201cMine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the Lord\u201d?", "answer": "The<b> Battle Hymn of the Republic</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Leaders of this nation derived their title from the phrase \u201ctent government.\u201d One leader of this nation won a battle through the ingenious use of arquebuses to puncture the armor</b> <b>of cavalry; his ally would win the Battle of (+)</b> <b>Sekigahara to take control of this nation</b> <b>and form a bakufu. Matthew (*)</b> Perry\u2019s black ships forced this nation to sign a treaty with the U.S., ending its isolationism. For ten points, name this country ruled by Oda Nobunaga and Tokugawa Ieyasu.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b> (accept<b> Nippon</b> or<b> Nihon</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Since 1977, the holder of this position has lived in Number One Observatory Circle on the grounds of the US Naval Observatory. Electoral votes are counted by the holder of this</b> <b>position. The Constitution did not explain how to (+)</b> <b>fill vacancies in this position until</b> <b>the 25th Amendment was ratified. The holder of this position also serves as (*)</b> President of the Senate, where they hold tiebreaking power. For ten points, name this office of the executive branch whose holder is first in line of Presidential succession.", "answer": "<b> Vice President</b> of the United States (prompt on \u201cVP(OTUS)\u201d) <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This country was once led by Pedro Lascurain, who ruled for less than an hour</b> <b>before resigning in the Ten Tragic Days. During that time, this country was the site</b> <b>of Victoriano (+)</b> <b>Huerta\u2019s military coup after Francisco Madero was assassinated,</b> <b>leading (*)</b> Emiliano Zapata and Pancho Villa to revolt. A 1910s revolution took place in, for ten points, what country that sold the Gadsden Purchase to its northern neighbor, the United States?", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}